<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vaida&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Vaida&#39;s Website</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-GB</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World</title>
      <link>/blog/hello_world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/hello_world/</guid>
      <description>This is going to be the first post published on this new iteration of my website. Fun fact, I had initially thought I&amp;rsquo;d be using Pika for my new homepage, and I&amp;rsquo;d recommend checking it out if you want a no-friction blogging tool! However, if I was going to start writing more, I wanted to do so with complete control of where my content was hosted and how it was rendered&amp;ndash; which meant going all-in on using Hugo (with the lovely Hugo ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ Bear Blog theme, which is inspired by another minimalist indie blogging platform, Bear Blog).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>About Welcome to Vaida&amp;rsquo;s personal website!
Personal I&amp;rsquo;m currently working out what my identity is in the present moment and in the present world, and how I can engage with the things I like in ways that make me happy. So, here&amp;rsquo;s a list of things I like:
Media - whether games, music, TV, or film, as long as it makes me feel something The outside world - this blog is an attempt to simplify my digital presence and separate myself from the feed, so I can spend more time outside meeting up with friends and doing things that make me feel alive Kindness and empathy baby!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
