<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Vaida Plankytė</title>
  <subtitle>Designer in Edinburgh, Scotland</subtitle>
  <link href="https://vaida.me/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://vaida.me/" />
  <updated>2026-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://vaida.me/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Vaida Plankytė</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>The Slow Game Club Report 1</title>
    <link href="https://vaida.me/blog/2026-02-22/slow-game-club-report-1/" />
    <updated>2026-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vaida.me/blog/2026-02-22/slow-game-club-report-1/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I got a membership for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slowgame.club/&quot;&gt;Slow Game Club&lt;/a&gt; this year, as a way to engage with games more intentionally; anything to lengthen that ol&#39; attention span! It&#39;s a charity fundraiser that funds games careers workshops for kids from low-income backgrounds in the UK, and in return, you receive 12 indie games, without knowing in advance which games you&#39;ll get throughout the year. As part of your membership, a game key lands in your mailbox at the start of each month, there&#39;s a Discord server to discuss the games as you play through them during the course of the month, and you even get a Q&amp;amp;A with the developers where they answer the server&#39;s questions!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game for January was &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/2366980/Thank_Goodness_Youre_Here/&quot;&gt;Thank Goodness You&#39;re Here!&lt;/a&gt;. It&#39;s not the kind of game I&#39;d pick up myself, so it was great to have an excuse to try something different. I enjoyed playing with a different kind of humour and going &amp;quot;oh god no&amp;quot; at the silliness. I&#39;ll spoil a bit of the game below so be warned!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While some gags might not have landed as well as others for me, it&#39;s such a compact game-- 3-ish hours, or longer if you&#39;re me and slowww-- that it doesn&#39;t feel like any gag overstays its welcome for too long. Playing this alongside a couple other games around the same time made me realise how much good pacing affects my enjoyment of a game, to the point that I can handle middling writing or writing that doesn&#39;t resonate with me much better than okay writing that Just. Drags. On. Maybe that just makes it not good writing in the first place tbf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise this sounds like &amp;quot;Vaida realised pacing is a key part of narrative design&amp;quot;, but I genuinely believed that I was more unforgiving of mid writing than I actually am. Turns out good pacing makes me go &amp;quot;okay the story is functional, it&#39;s there to move me to this next bit, fair enough. It&#39;s not your strength, and you&#39;re not trying to convince me that it is&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few examples of this, I dropped &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1346020/Wargroove_2/&quot;&gt;Wargroove 2&lt;/a&gt; because the introductory narrative sections were so boring to get through, and I&#39;m not one for skipping story outright; in comparison, a game like &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/761030/EARTHLOCK/&quot;&gt;EARTHLOCK&lt;/a&gt; has a pretty classic story and characters, but it&#39;s funny and lets me get on with playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As my friend Lisa told me when I shared these thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;If you&#39;re going to be uninteresting, at least don&#39;t be boring&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lisa (who always says it best)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But back to Thank Goodness You&#39;re Here!. It did have some excellent jokes, and a richness of details in each scene, so there was always &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that worked for me in a scene, especially the ramping up of situations that you keep revisiting. I&#39;m still laughing at &amp;quot;Closed due to smacky bum bums :(&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also so confident, and doesn&#39;t mind people discounting it as &amp;quot;oh haha funny game&amp;quot; at first and then surprising you with the direction it takes with the ending sequence; it&#39;s happy to lose some people by not revealing its cards too early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s cool how rooted in a specific place this game is, that makes for a much more interesting experience than a generic (probably American) Town in Game, and the fact it very much is spoken in a dialect of that place. The authenticity being more important than understandability or a watering down, and something that players appreciate and can engage with. There&#39;s an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pcgamer.com/games/adventure/how-translators-performed-the-herculean-task-of-localizing-the-most-incomprehensibly-british-videogame-of-all-time-into-german-portuguese-and-traditional-chinese-what-on-earth-are-these-characters-even-talking-about/&quot;&gt;article about how the game&#39;s regionalisms and humour got localised&lt;/a&gt; that I&#39;ve yet to fully read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, how &amp;quot;slap&amp;quot; as the main verb frames every single interaction with the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also also, one of my questions got answered by the devs! Fun! I asked why the Scottish plumber, who spoke with a heavy Scottish accent, spoke Scottish English rather than speaking Scots, as my Scots-speaking partner watched me play a bit of the game and had remarked that it it&#39;d feel more authentic that way, especially with the vibe the game was already going for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on Slow Game Club overall, I find Discord communities overwhelming when they&#39;re too active, so I&#39;m glad this server isn&#39;t super busy. I think it&#39;s because it&#39;s gated by a donation, so skews towards an older demographic that doesn&#39;t clog up the server with memeposting; a lot of people just lurk and play the games. There&#39;s lots of thoughtful, evolving discussion over the month, and that&#39;s exactly what I was hoping for. I&#39;ve been really worn out by social media, and trying to increase prolonged engagement with media I consume rather than jumping around to the next thing, so it&#39;s nice to have an outlet for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t finish the game, and initially I felt like I should do so ahead of the dev interview to &amp;quot;make the most out of it&amp;quot; but then I snapped out of it. I got the enjoyment I wanted from it! I can both enjoy a game and also decide I don&#39;t really want to see any more of it at this point in time! I find it really hard to leave things &amp;quot;unfinished&amp;quot;, so learning how to drop a game or how to return to it without frustrating myself are things I want to practise more. There&#39;s a channel for discussing the game with spoilers and one without, and I kept myself from reading the spoilers channel as I wanted to finish the game first, but that meant missing out on conversation. I think in future months I&#39;ll let myself &amp;quot;give up&amp;quot; on a game earlier, so I can read the spoilered chat earlier. So I&#39;m really treating this as meta-learning of how I approach games and being more chill with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;February&#39;s game is &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1796580/Sorry_Were_Closed/&quot;&gt;Sorry We&#39;re Closed&lt;/a&gt;, which I loved playing through in December (those character portraits, oof) and I&#39;m not one for replaying games much, especially so soon, so instead I took the chance to try out one of the bonus games (we got some unused keys from the previous year&#39;s edition), &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1160220/Paradise_Killer/&quot;&gt;Paradise Killer&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;m really surprised by how much I&#39;m enjoying it! Mixing visual novel sections with 3D world traversal works like a charm for switching between two different modes of thinking and resting your brain, and give you a chance to form theories. I kept thinking I&#39;d get stuck or disengaged, but things kept moving and a really satisfying mystery was built up. I&#39;ve just got the final bit to go through. Paradise will be saved... or will it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This month, I watched a video about the &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/m3SEgn4Gehw?si=Yi8iiRIE8Hb9f2EP&quot;&gt;Dialectics of Go&lt;/a&gt; that someone from the server recommended; it was an excellent watch, with the joining up of theories across various fields. Meanwhile, someone else said that after a conversation we had and watching some dev interviews, they&#39;d changed their opinion on an aspect of Sorry We&#39;re Closed. People engaging with each other over time, coming out changed! It&#39;s what Jenny Odell said would happen...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Sensitivity, in contrast, involves a difficult, awkward, ambiguous encounter between two differently shaped bodies that are themselves ambiguous — and this meeting, this sensing, requires and takes place in time. Not only that, due to the effort of sensing, the two entities might come away from the encounter a bit differently than they went in.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jenny Odell, &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@the_jennitaur/how-to-do-nothing-57e100f59bbb&quot;&gt;how to do nothing&lt;/a&gt; (I&#39;ve read the book when in university and have been referencing it everywhere since)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was thinking of looking up alternate endings and checking out the artbook for the game; the dev interview is next week so maybe I&#39;ll do it before then or maybe I won&#39;t. I think I know what next month&#39;s game will be as a few games are revealed due to being in the advertising material for the club. If so, I&#39;ve already played it as well (woa watch out, hashtag indie games nerd over here!!), so I might dig into some more articles that the game studies person from the server linked to, or something else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can join &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.slowgame.club/&quot;&gt;Slow Game Club&lt;/a&gt; and still get keys for these first two games, if you&#39;re interested!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ECGx 2025</title>
    <link href="https://vaida.me/blog/2025-06-28/ecgx-2025/" />
    <updated>2025-06-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://vaida.me/blog/2025-06-28/ecgx-2025/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this month I went to &lt;a href=&quot;https://scottishgames.net/2025/05/30/ecgx-2025-edinburgh-college-games-expo/&quot;&gt;ECGx&lt;/a&gt;, a yearly showcase for the Edinburgh College Games course, with space for local devs to show their work as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to see regulars of the Edinburgh indie scene again; though the event was on for just an hour and a half, so it was a struggle to catch up &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; play some games &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; talk to new people! I got compliments on my Neon Genesis Evangelion t-shirt (courtesy of UNIQLO, grab it while stocks last), and shamed when I admitted I hadn&#39;t actually seen it yet. It&#39;s on my list! I&#39;ll get to it! I want to finish Cowboy Bebop first...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are pictures of some of the games I played:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Give up the Ghost by Either/Or Collective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/gutg_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Give up the Ghost on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Give up the Ghost on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/gutg_2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Give up the Ghost on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Give up the Ghost on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://playgiveuptheghost.com/&quot;&gt;Give up the Ghost&lt;/a&gt; is a black-and-white RPG that is inspired by Disco Elysium, with really lovely art (look at that character design in the second image!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked how it approaches the character setup. You start by picking a &amp;quot;way of seeing&amp;quot;, I chose Hindsight: &amp;quot;history reveals itself to you (...) but regret will haunt you.&amp;quot; The narrative tone is clear from the very first explanatory text!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played just a bit before deciding I liked it and wanted to check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://eitherorcollective.itch.io/giveup-alpha&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt; at home instead to properly enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Upfall and CRT7 by Amicable Animal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/upfall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Upfall on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Upfall on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/3570280/Upfall/&quot;&gt;Upfall&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/2096780/CRT7/&quot;&gt;CRT7&lt;/a&gt; have focused gameplay and polished glowy graphics-- it&#39;s a signature style! Upfall is free to play, while CRT7 is still in development, with a demo available. Excited to see where it takes things...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Three Mushketeers by Georgia Cairns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/thethreemushketeers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The Three Mushketeers on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;The Three Mushketeers on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a charming game about three mushrooms with different powers, and Georgia made all of the art! This reminded me of the &amp;quot;games for girls&amp;quot; of the 90s-- specifically the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dca.org.uk/exhibition-archive/theresa-duncan/&quot;&gt;DCA exhibition&lt;/a&gt; on Theresa Duncan I went to in 2016. I really liked Chop Suey-- here&#39;s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PWV-5_r0gNU&quot;&gt;longplay&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;d recommend even skimming through it, it&#39;s a great reset if you get stuck in thinking that games need to be a certain way. I&#39;ve been feeling the same perspective reset when checking out &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.date/games/seasons/two/&quot;&gt;Season 2&lt;/a&gt; PlayDate games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Psychosis by Aaron Gilbert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/psychosis.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Psychosis on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Psychosis on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This horror game has some gnarly monster designs and lovely low-res textures. I enjoyed watching someone else fight off abominations while trying to find a key (I don&#39;t think they were successful). An early version is &lt;a href=&quot;https://store.steampowered.com/app/1922550/Psychosis/&quot;&gt;available to play&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Exon by Rao Dao Zao&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/exon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Exon on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Exon on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exon is a narrative mech action-cRPG and I love how the graphics are unapologetically Of An Era and very cohesive. There&#39;s an &lt;a href=&quot;https://raodaozao.itch.io/exon-fragment&quot;&gt;older demo&lt;/a&gt; to try, and I also want to mention Rao Dao Zao&#39;s long-running &lt;a href=&quot;https://raodaozao.net/&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt;. It is &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.vbuckenham.com/the-year-of-the-blog/&quot;&gt;the year of the blog&lt;/a&gt;, after all! What you&#39;re reading right now-- it is, indeed, also a blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scandimania&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/scandimania.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Scandimania on a desktop&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Scandimania on a desktop&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a student project that&#39;s not online yet and I didn&#39;t catch the team name. While the gameplay was clunky, the graphics and textures were effective at setting a Dark Souls-y mood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character is made up of light, and instead of a healthbar, your character&#39;s brightness decreases as you get hurt. That&#39;s a cool idea. It was also cool to see what students without formal compsci training and who hadn&#39;t coded before can achieve over the course of a year. You can learn a lot in a short span of time! It is easy to forget, especially as you get older and have less free time, that learning new things is still very much possible and it might not even take that long to get somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus: Cosmic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://vaida.me/assets/blog/ecgx-2025/cosmic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Cosmic placard with instructions and a low-poly alien inviting you to play the game&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;Cosmic placard with instructions and a low-poly alien inviting you to play the game&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the event was wrapping up and we were ushered to leave, I noticed this placard-sign-thing with what might be the most enticing invitation to play-slash-controls guide ever. I&#39;m not sure if it&#39;s available online, as it&#39;s a student game and &amp;quot;Cosmic&amp;quot; is a very broad search term. Perhaps this game will forever remain a mystery to me...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading! If you&#39;re interested in getting involved with the Edinburgh indie scene, I&#39;d recommend checking out the various links on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://edindi.es/&quot;&gt;edindies&lt;/a&gt; website, and joining the Discord!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>